Finding Aid for Harold S. Gray Papers 1896-1972.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Harold S. Gray Papers 1896-1972
Gray, Harold Studley, 1894-1972.
6 motion picture reels
2 oversize volumes
1 oversize folder
12.5 linear feet
Conscientious objector during World Wars I and II and founder of the farming cooperative Saline Valley Farms. Correspondence, diaries, notebooks, and other materials relating to all phases of his career, including his work as Y.M.C.A. worker in England, 1916-1917, and as teacher at Central China University, Wuchang, China, 1922-1926; also family correspondence of Philip H. and Almena S. Gray, 1874-1926; also photographs and motion pictures.
851418 Aa 2 UAm
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Harold Gray (donor no. 3393 ) and came to the library in 1969 and 1972.
The collection is open for research.
The 16mm films and two-inch videotapes in the collection were digitized in 2009 as part of a library video preservation project. Preservation master beta tapes for all titles and high resolution digital files of some titles were created along with DVD and streaming files for all titles. The DVDs are available for use in the library. A selection of the streaming files may be available online at a given time, others can be mounted on request.
Harold Studley Gray was the developer and owner of the Saline Valley Farms, an experiment in cooperative farming and living. Born in Detroit, February 23, 1894, Gray was a graduate of Exeter Academy, then attended Harvard University as war broke out in Europe. Leaving school, he volunteered for duty with the Young Men's Christian Association in England working in a German prisoner-of-war camp. His experiences during this time led Gray to take a stand for non-violence. When he returned to the United States, he was drafted but he claimed exemption on the grounds of conscientious objection. After a court-martial, Gray was sentenced to life imprisonment (later commuted to twenty-five years at hard labor). In 1919, he was dismissed dishonorably from military service.
After his release, he returned to Harvard, receiving his A.B. and M.A. degrees. He next went to China where for four years he taught economics in Central China University, Wuchang, China. During his time in England and while in prison, Gray began developing ideas for an experiment in social farming and economic security. He had some thought that this might be possible in China. But when revolutions in China made this impossible, Gray began to contemplate a similar venture in the United States. In 1932, he purchased farm land acreage near Saline, Michigan. The land included an abandoned farmhouse and barn. His goal was to raise the standards of agricultural life by combining farming and industry, selling the product of the farm directly to the consumer.
One of the aims of Saline Valley Farms cooperative was to provide a measure of economic security during this time of depression. Gray sought to employ as many people as possible in marketing the products of the farm. The Saline site was chosen because of its proximity to the Detroit area and to the University of Michigan. Many of Gray's first employees were of high-school age. Their work on the farm, Gray believed, would enable them to stay in school and to earn sufficient income that they could to go to college.
Many of the people employed at the Farms brought valuable training and experience. One, Harold Vaughn, was a former county agricultural agent hired by Gray to be farm manager. Vaughn devoted his time during this early period to planting orchards, assembling machinery and livestock, and preparing the land. With their work and planning and with the efforts of the other members of the cooperative, the Saline Valley Farms grew but never really prospered financially. The depression was in part responsible for the early success of the Farms. At the close of World War II, Gray confronted the unsteady economic state of the operation. Workers were able to get better wages outside; Gray had difficulty getting people to work for him at the prices he could afford to pay. Finally, in 1953, he decided to abandon the program and in 1959 the cooperative was formally dissolved.
Gray kept the property until 1969 when he sold it to the Teamsters Union for their use as a recreational and retirement center.
Gray died April 5, 1972.
The Harold Gray papers have been divided into seven series: Correspondence; World War I era activities; Personal and Miscellaneous; Printed, clippings, and miscellanea; Family and genealogical; Saline Valley Farms; and Visual Materials (photographs and motion pictures). The great strength of the collection are correspondence, administrative files, diaries, and visual materials documenting the operation of the Saline Valley Farms. There is significant, though smaller quantities of papers detailing Gray's opposition to serving in the military during World War I and his career as a teacher in China in the 1920s.
Subjects:
China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; The Christian century.; Columbia Conserve Company.; Conscientious objectors.; Cooperative societies--Michigan--Saline.; England.; Farm life--Michigan--Saline.; Fellowship of Reconciliation (U.S.); Gray, Almena Studley.; Gray, Harold Studley, 1894-1972.; Gray, John Simpson, 1841-1906.; Gray, Philip Hayward, 1865-1922.; Pacifism.; Saline (Mich.); Saline Valley Farms (Saline, Mich.); World War, 1914-1918.; Young Men's Christian Associations.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Agriculture--Michigan.; Au Sable River (Mich.); Charlevoix (Mich.); China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Cooperatives.; Detroit (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Dwellings--Michigan--Detroit.; Dwellings.; Farms.; Gray, Harold Studley, 1894-1972.; Interiors.; Mackinac Island (Mich.); Oscoda (Mich.); Petoskey (Mich.); Prisoners of war--United States.; Recreation.; Resorts--Michigan.; Saline Valley Farms (Saline, Mich.); Studley family.; Traffic accidents.; World War, 1914-1918.
Subjects - Sound Recordings
Gray, Harold Studley, 1894-1972.; Saline Valley Farms (Saline, Mich.); Vaughn, Marian.
Contributors:
Allinson, Brent Dow.; Baldwin, Roger N. (Roger Nash), 1884-1981; Bennett, James O'Donnell, 1870-1940.; Chaplin, Maxwell.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Crane, Henry Hitt, 1890-1977.; Dunham, Arthur, 1893-; Eddy, Sherwood, 1871-1963.; Fey, Harold E. (Harold Edward), 1898-1990; Hapgood, William Powers, 1872-1960.; Hennacy, Ammon, 1893-1970.; Jones, Edgar De Witt, 1876-1956.; Jones, Paul, 1880-1941.; Libby, Frederick J. (Frederick Joseph), 1874-1970; Lunde, Erling H.; Morrison, Charles Clayton, 1874-1966; Mott, John Raleigh, 1865-1955.; Muste, Abraham John, 1885-1967.; Nelson, Walter Morrow.; Page, Kirby, 1890-1957.; Porter, David R.; Sayre, John Nevin, 1884-1977.; Shaw, Mark Revell, 1889-; Swomley, John M., 1915-2010; Thomas, Emma Mattoon.; Thomas, Evan W. (Evan Welling), 1890-1974.; Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968.; Vaughan, Harold M.; Zhang, Fuliang, b. 1889.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Motion pictures.; Photographs.; Sound recordings.; Videotapes.
- Correspondence
  - General
    - Undated 1896-February 1917, 33 folders (Box 1)
    - March 1917-1926, 38 folders (Box 2)
    - 1927-1943, 39 folders (Box 3)
    - 1944-1971, 11 folders (Box 4)
  - Family correspondence
    - Undated 1874-1918, 21 folders (Box 4)
    - 1919-1926, 7 folders (Box 5)
- World War I Era
  - Y.M.C.A. work in England 1916-1917, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Induction into the armed services and subsequent court-martial 1917-1918 (Box 5)
  - Release from prison 1919 (Box 5)
  - Pamphlet by Mrs. Henry Hobhouse: I Appeal Unto Caesar, undated (Box 5)
  - Printed material concerning the treatment of conscientious objectors 1918-1919, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Typescript copies of letters from Gray to his family 1916-1918, 1 notebook (Box 5)
- Personal and miscellaneous
  - Record of personal expenditures 1912-1914 (Box 5)
  - Record of personal expenditures 1915-1917 (Box 5)
  - Student notebook undated (Box 5)
  - Notebook of poems, quotations, lists of operas attended, and other miscellanea 1921 (Box 5)
  - Master's thesis "A Report on the Causes of Overpopulation in China" 1922, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook containing reviews Character "Bad", 1933-1934 (Box 5)
  - Book reviews of Character "Bad", 1934 (Box 5)
  - Speech: "Does Jesus have the Answer to War?" 1939 (Box 5)
  - Paper: "Statement on War and Conscription" 1942 (Box 5)
  - Paper "Statement on War and Conscription" 1942 [Preliminary draft] (Box 5)
  - Church bulletins 1965-1969 (Box 5)
    (written by Harold Gray)
  - Diaries, 1933-1957 (Box 6)
  - Diaries, 1958-1972 (Box 7)
- Printed, clippings, and miscellanea
  - Printed materials undated, 1906-1970, 5 folders (Box 8)
  - Newspaper clippings 1884-1969, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Miscellanea undated, 1906-1968, 3 folders (Box 8)
- Family and genealogical
  - Journal concerning the Gray family lodge "Oak Camp" at Lake Angeles 1881-1911 (Box 8)
  - Genealogical notebook undated (Box 8)
  - Genealogical papers 1931-1940, undated (Box 8)
  - Genealogy of the family of Anna Eliza Hayward undated (Box 8)
  - Scrapbook of Anna Hayward Gray concerning the death of John S. Gray 1906 (Volume 1)
  - Papers concerning the schooling of son, William Gray 1940-1943 (Box 8)
  - Papers concerning the estate of Philip H. Gray 1922-1937, 4 folders (Box 8)
  - Papers concerning Gray's views on marriage and marital difficulties 1935-1947, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Books by David Gray (2) (Box 8)
  - Book: Letters of Maxwell Chaplin edited by George Stewart (Box 8)
- Saline Valley Farms File
  - Historical sketches 1938-1942, undated (Box 9)
  - Annual reports 1937-1941 (Box 9)
  - Annual reports 1942-1946 (Box 9)
  - Papers undated, 1932-1954, 27 folders (Box 9)
  - Papers 1955-1970, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Newspaper clippings 1934-1959 (Box 10)
  - Newspaper clippings 1960-1970 (Box 10)
  - Newspaper clippings miscellaneous (various dates) (Box 10)
  - Notebook concerning lands considered for purchase for Saline Valley Farms 1931 (Box 10)
  - Papers concerning visitors to the farm 1936-1944, 7 folders (Box 10)
  - Guest register 1934-1941 (Box 10)
  - Guest register 1946-1954 (Box 10)
  - Inventory 1933 (Box 10)
  - Account book 1937-1942 (Box 10)
  - Job applications 1936-1944 (Box 10)
  - Letters of recommendation 1940-1944 (Box 10)
  - Financial balance sheets 1948-1953 (Box 10)
  - SVF personnel (Box 10)
  - Delivery routes 1944-1945, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Sales tax paid 1942-1945, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Scrapbook concerning Saline Valley Farms 1932-1940 (Box 10)
    (taken apart; contents put in folder)
  - Financial ledger Saline Valley Farms (Volume 2)
  - Maps and blueprints (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous Saline Valley Farms materials (Box 10)
  - Articles of Incorporation and minute book of the Saline Valley Farms Co-operative, Inc. 1944-1954 (Box 11)
  - Stock certificates-Saline Valley Farm Co-Operative, Inc (Box 11)
  - Minute book 1935-1939, 1947-1953, 2 volumes (Box 11)
  - Account books (Box 11)
  - Payroll time sheets (Box 11)
- Visual Materials
  The Visual Materials series includes photographs and motion pictures depicting activities at Saline Valley Farms; photos of Michigan residences and of his work as teacher in China, 1922-1926; and photos of a World War I prisoner of war camp. The photos, arranged in two files, were collected by Gray and by Russell Bidlack. The six 16mm films (which have been digitized and are available on dvd and as streaming files) record a range of farm activities, buildings and workers. The collection includes an audiotape recording of commentary by Marian Vaughn, participant in the Saline Valley Farm, on scenes in the films.
  - Photographs
    - Photographs accumulated by Harold Gray
      (see also oversize folder UAm)
      - Automobile accident at lake (Box 12)
      - China, etc. (taken from album); also family photographs (Box 12)
      - Detroit 1909 (Box 12)
      - Family: group photographs (Box 12)
      - Family: individual photographs (Box 12)
      - Harold Gray, portraits (Box 12)
      - Hayo-Went-Ha, Charlevoix, and Petoskey (Box 12)
      - Mackinac Island (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
      - Nissokone (Box 12)
      - Nissokone, taken by Harry Cohn 1920-1921 (Box 12)
      - Residences: Gray home in Detroit (Box 12)
      - Residences: miscellaneous (Box 12)
      - St. Lawrence trip (Box 12)
      - Saline Valley Farms
        - Buildings, main group (Box 12)
        - Buildings, miscellaneous (Box 12)
        - Farm animals (Box 12)
        - Farm work, miscellaneous (Box 12)
        - Field work (Box 12)
        - Harold Gray and others (Box 12)
        - Homes (Box 12)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
        - Planting and harvesting hay (Box 12)
        - Poultry (Box 12)
        - Scenic views (Box 12)
        - Social gatherings (Box 12)
      - World War I prisoner of war camp
        - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
        - Buildings and interiors (Box 12)
        - Daily life, 2 folders (Box 12)
        - Group photographs (Box 12)
      - Y.M.C.A. Vanettan Lake, Oscoda, Michigan (Box 12)
    - Saline Valley Farms Photographs
      (collected by Russell Bidlack)
      - Agricultural Subjects
        - General Cultivating and Harvesting (Box 12)
        - Dairying (Box 12)
        - Farm Buildings (Box 12)
        - Food Processing (Box 12)
        - Horses (Box 12)
          see also Cultivating and Harvesting
        - Main Building and Store (Box 12)
        - Orchards (Box 12)
        - Poultry
          - General, including Hatchery (Box 12)
          - Houses-exteriors (Box 12)
          - Houses-interiors (Box 12)
          - Chickens (Box 12)
          - Specimens (Box 12)
          - Sheep (Box 12)
      - Children (Box 12)
      - Families (Box 12)
      - Groups
        - Large (Box 12)
        - Small (Box 12)
      - Individuals
        - Men (Box 12)
        - Women (Box 12)
      - Living quarters (Box 12)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
      - Recreation (Box 12)
      - Views
        - General (Box 12)
        - Winter (Box 12)
      - Water-Water control (Box 12)
    - Photograph albums
      - World War I conscientious objectors (Box 13)
      - Saline Valley Farms (Box 13)
  - Motion Pictures, 6 reels
    - Saline Valley Farms [No. 1] 1930s, 851418-1
      - Original:, 16mm film, color, pos, silent, 00:28:11 @ 18fps
        [Restricted]
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 851418-1, flash-flv
    - Saline Valley Farms [No. 2] 1930s, 851418-2
      - Original:, 16mm film, color, pos, silent, 00:54:51 @ 18 fps
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 851418-2, flash-flv
    - Saline Valley Farms [No. 3] 1930s, 851418-3
      - Original:, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:50:55 @ 18fps.
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 851418-3, flash-flv
    - Saline Valley Farms [No. 4] 1930s, 851418-4
      - Original:, 16mm film, color, pos, silent, 00:50:55 @ 18fps.
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 851418-4, flash-flv
    - Saline Valley Farms [No. 5] 1930s, 851418-5
      - Original:, 16mm film, color, pos, silent, 00:41:05@ 18 fps.
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 851418-5, flash-flv
    - Saline Valley Farms [No. 6] 1930s, 851418-6
      - Original:, 16mm film, b/w, pos, silent, 00:58:00 at 18 fps.
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 851418-6, flash-flv
  - Sound recording and shot list
    - Sound recording commentary by Marian Vaughn on the motion pictures (Box 13)
    - Shot list to the motion pictures (Box 13)
      (listing probably compiled from sound recording of Marian Vaughn)
Selective Index of Correspondents
Allinson, Brent Dow
Sept. 26, 1942, Jan. 8, 1943
Baldwin, Roger Nash, 1884-
Aug. 28, 1918, Aug. 31, 1918, Apr. 28, 1942, Dec. 27, 1949, Jan. 3, 1954, Jan. 9, 1956
Bennett, James O'Donnell, 1870-1940.
June 11, 1934
Chang, Fu Liang
1922-1937, 1948, 1950-1952, 1959-1960, 1962-1967, 1969-1971
Chaplin, Maxwell
1916-1919, 1920's undated, 1920-1921, 1923, 1926
Couzens, James Joseph, 1872-1936.
Aug. 5, 1914, July 31, 1918, May 16, 1930
Crane, Henry Hitt, 1890-
June 6, 1934, 1936, 1939, Mar. 4, 1940, Feb. 19, 1941, 1947
Dunham, Arthur, 1893-
Apr. 17, 1919, Jan. 13, 1920, Nov. 16, 1935, 1952-1955, 1957, 1959, 1965
Eddy, Sherwood, 1871-1963.
Sept. 1, 1916, Apr. 15, 1921, Oct. 4, 1921, Jan. 2, 1931, Apr. 15, 1932, 1935-1936, Dec. 10, 1937, 1950's undated, Feb. 15, 1951, Feb. 24, 1956, Oct. 5, 1957
Fey, Harold Edward, 1898-
1936, Mar. 2, 1939, 1942, 1963
Hapgood, William Powers, 1872-1960.
1931-1933
Hennacy, Ammon A., 1893-1970.
1934, Dec. 19, 1941, 1942, Dec. 19, 1947, Sept. 26, 1949, May 1, 1954, 1955, July 3, 1956, 1961-1968
Jones, Edgar DeWitt, 1876-1956.
1926-1927, Feb. 5, 1934, May 7, 1934, May 17, 1934, Feb. 19, 1936, Mar. 21, 1939, Apr. 28, 1942, Sept. 18, 1945, June 22, 1949, Dec. 1, 1949
Jones, Paul, 1880-1941.
Sept. 16, 1921, Oct. 28, 1921, Nov. 9, 1921
Libby, Frederick Joseph, 1874-
1931-1932, Aug. 30, 1934, 1940-1942, 1945-1946, 1953-1954, 1957-1959, 1961-1966, 1968
Lunde, Erling H.
Dec. 28, 1929, Mar. 25, 1939, 1941, Feb. 2, 1952, Dec. 15, 1962
Morrison, Charles Clayton, 1874-1966.
Mar. 22 and 26, 1919, July 29, 1919, Dec. 13, 1924, June 3, 1929, Feb. 3, 1930, Feb. 19, 1934, June 18, 1934, Dec. 31, 1934, Mar. 26, 1954, Mar. 7, 1955, Apr. 16, 1958
Mott, John Raleigh, 1865-1955.
1917, Dec. 9, 1918, Nov. 22, 1921
Muste, Abraham John, 1885-1967.
1940-1943, Nov. 27, 1945, 1946, 1950-1952
Nelson, Walter Morrow
May 20, 1942
Page, Kirby, 1890-1957.
Undated, 1916-1929, 1930's undated, 1930-1939, 1940's undated, 1941-1945, 1947-1948, 1952-1953, 1955-1956
Porter, David R
Undated, 1913-1919, 1920's undated, 1920-1942, Dec. 16, 1945, 1946, Dec. 1, 1948, Dec. 20, 1949, Dec. 12, 1952, Dec. 12, 1953, Dec. 10, 1954, Dec. 9, 1955, Dec. 15, 1957, Jan. 18, 1965
Sayre, John Nevin, 1884-
Sept. 26, 1921, May 1, 1928, June 8, 1934, Jan. 19, 1938, May 15, 1939, June 16, 1939, June 14, 1940, Jan. 3, 1941, Apr. 29, 1942, Oct. 25, 1945, Feb. 18, 1954
Shaw, Mark Revell, 1889-
Dec. 3, 1956
Sunday, William A.
March 3, 1921
Swomley, John M., 1915-
Jan. 24, 1950, July 22, 1955
Thomas, Emma (Mattoon)
Aug. 31, 1918, Sept. 4, 1918
Thomas, Evan Welling, 1890-
1919, 1942, May 11, 1943, 1944, Dec. 23, 1955, 1960's undated, Dec. 21, 1962, 1963
Thomas, Norman Mattoon, 1884-1968.
July 16, 1918, Mar. 24, 1930, Jan. 27, 1932, Jan. 24, 1933, Feb. 4, 1933, Feb. 5, 1938, July 19, 1938, Feb. 25, 1940, May 15, 1941, Aug. 2, 1941, Oct. 30, 1941, Feb. 24, 1942